Guide to the South West Pennsylvania and Eureka Pipe Line Companies Records, 1889-1928 AIS.1964.11
ULS Archives & Special Collections
South West Pennsylvania and Eureka Pipe Line Companies Records
1889-1928
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Eureka Pipe Line Company.
South West Pennsylvania Pipe Line Company.
AIS.1964.11
11.25 Linear Feet (100 volumes)
This collection of records pertains to five pipe line companies: Eureka Pipe Line Company, South West Pennsylvania Pipe Line Company, Buckeye Pipe Line Company, Cumberland Pipe Line Company, and Southern Pipe Line Company. The collection contains varied forms of ledgers including letter/copy books, financial ledgers, production/inventory ledgers, balance books, check books, and rental ledgers.
Acquisition Information
Gift of R.L. Lockwood on February 3, 1964.
Previous Citation
South West Pennsylvania and Eureka Pipe Line Companies Records, 1889-1928, AIS.1964.11, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Access Restrictions
No restrictions; however, users of this collection must make an appointment with the Archives Service Center before the collection can be serviced because of its current physical arrangment.
History
This collection of records pertains to five pipe line companies: Eureka Pipe Line Company, South West Pennsylvania Pipe Line Company, Buckeye Pipe Line Company, Cumberland Pipe Line Company, and Southern Pipe Line Company. The earliest records in the collection are those that belong to Eureka (1889). Most of the records detail Eureka's layout of oil pipelines for businesses in Allegheny and the surrounding counties. Essentially Eureka's pipelines were transporting unrefined oil from Oil City, Pa., which was then either used to power factories and farms, or was refined into gasoline for commercial transportation. The company dealt exclusively with the James Brothers' lumber and manufacturing companies.
Arrangement
The records are organized into seven series:
Series I. Letter/Copy Books, 1889-1924
Series II. Purchase and Collection Reports and Transfers, 1897-1924
Series III. Production, Inventory, and Shipping Ledgers, 1891-1928
Series IV. Balance Books, Check Stub Books, and Vouchers, 1895-1923
Series V. Rentals, 1906-1922
Series VI. Contacts and Address Ledgers
Series VII. Material in Boxes
Scope and Content Notes
Most of the records in the collection, including all of the ledgers, deal with the Eureka and South West Pennsylvania Pipe Line Companies. Series VIII deals with the Southern Pipe Line Company. The six record center boxes in Series VIII contain the records of the first four companies mentioned in the history. Located in the boxes are several blueprint maps that show the layout of Pipe Lines in Allegheny County. The collection contains varied forms of ledgers including letter/copy books, financial ledgers, production/inventory ledgers, balance books, check books, and rental ledgers. Additional scope notes are found at the series level.
Petroleum pipelines -- Pennsylvania; Petroleum pipeline industry -- Pennsylvania; Ledgers (Account books); Business and Industry; Buckeye Pipe Line Company.; Cumberland Pipe Line Company.; Eureka Pipe Line Company.; South West Pennsylvania Pipe Line Company.; Southern Pipe Line Company.
- Letter/Copy Books, 1889-1924; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I consists of letter/copy books used by the Eureka Pipe Line Company during the years 1889 to 1924. These contain letters detailing work carried out that accompanied payments to Eureka.
  - Letter/Copy Book, 1889-1905 (Volume 1)
  - Letter/Copy Book, 1893-1896 (Volume 2)
  - Letter/Copy Book, 1903-1906 (Volume 3)
  - Letter/Copy Book, 1905 (Volume 4)
  - Letter/Copy Book, 1905-1908 (Volume 5)
  - Letter/Copy Book, 1906 (Volume 6)
  - Letter/Copy Book, 1907 (Volume 7)
  - Letter/Copy Book, 1908 (Volume 8)
  - Letter/Copy Book, 1911-1912 (Volume 9)
  - Letter/Copy Book, 1911-1917 (Volume 10)
  - Letter/Copy Book, 1912-1913 (Volume 11)
  - Letter/Copy Book, 1914-1915 (Volume 12)
  - Letter/Copy Book, 1914-1919 (Volume 13)
  - Letter/Copy Book, 1916-1917 (Volume 14)
  - Letter/Copy Book, 1918-1920 (Volume 15)
  - Letter/Copy Book, 1919-1920 (Volume 16)
  - Letter/Copy Book, 1920-1924 (Volume 17)
- Purchase and Collection Reports and Transfers, 1897-1924; II.
  This series contains Purchase and Collection Reports and Transfers of the Eureka Pipe Line Company. This type of ledger details the financial status of the company in the transportation of oil, purchase of land, lay of pipe, overall profit, and employee payroll.
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, July 1897-November 1900 (Volume 18)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, October 1908 (Volume 19)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, November-December 1908 (Volume 20)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, January-February 1909 (Volume 21)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, March-April 1909 (Volume 22)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, July 1909 (Volume 23)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, August-November 1909 (Volume 24)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, 1909 (Volume 25)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, 1909-1911 (Volume 26)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, March 1910 (Volume 27)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, April 1910 (Volume 28)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, August-October 1910 (Volume 29)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, November 1910 (Volume 30)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, November 1910-January 1911 (Volume 31)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, February-May 1911 (Volume 32)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, August-September 1911 (Volume 33)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, October-November 1911 (Volume 34)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, December 1911-January 1912 (Volume 35)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, 1911-1914 (Volume 36)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, February-March 1912 (Volume 37)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, April-May 1912 (Volume 38)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, June-July 1912 (Volume 39)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, August-November 1912 (Volume 40)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, December 1912-January 1913 (Volume 41)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, February-March 1913 (Volume 42)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, April-May 1913 (Volume 43)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, June-July 1913 (Volume 44)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, October-November 1913 (Volume 45)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, December 1913-January 1914 (Volume 46)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, February 1914 (Volume 47)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, April-May 1914 (Volume 48)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, June-July 1914 (Volume 49)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, August-September 1914 (Volume 50)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, October-November 1914 (Volume 51)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, December 1914-January 1915 (Volume 52)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, February-March 1915 (Volume 53)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, June-July 1915 (Volume 54)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, August-September 1915 (Volume 55)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, October-November 1915 (Volume 56)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, December 1915-January 1916 (Volume 57)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, April-May 1916 (Volume 58)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, June-July, November 1916 (Volume 59)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, August-September 1916 (Volume 60)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, August-September 1916 (Volume 61)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, October-December 1916 (Volume 62)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, January-February 1917 (Volume 63)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, March-April 1917 (Volume 64)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, May-June 1917 (Volume 65)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, July-August 1917 (Volume 66)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, September-October 1917 (Volume 67)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, November-December 1917 (Volume 68)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, March-April 1918 (Volume 69)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, May-June 1918 (Volume 70)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, September-October 1918 (Volume 71)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, January-February 1919 (Volume 72)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, March-April 1919 (Volume 73)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, May-June 1919 (Volume 74)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, July-August 1919 (Volume 75)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, September-October 1919 (Volume 76)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, November-December 1919 (Volume 77)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, March-April 1920 (Volume 78)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, May-June 1920 (Volume 79)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, July-August 1920 (Volume 80)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, September-October 1920 (Volume 81)
  - Purchase and collection reports and transfers, 1924; (longer ledger book, different format) (Volume 82)
- Production, Inventory, and Shipping Ledgers, 1891-1928; III.
  Series III contains records that detail production, shipping and receiving practices of the Eureka Pipe Line Company.
  - Loose pages, Eureka P.L. Co., release/hold ledger (shipping/receiving/inventory), 1891-1904 (Volume 83)
  - Production List/Inventory-monthly sales/loss, contains blueprint, 1897 (Volume 84)
  - Consolidated Chemical Co., Kane, Pa. - received/delivered book, transfers, 1898-1906 (Volume 85)
  - Pool & Material Book (inventory), 1909-1915 (Volume 86)
  - Shipping/Receiving Ledger, 1914-1919 (Volume 87)
  - Invoice copies - many deal with James Bros. Mfg. Co., 1914-1919 (Volume 89)
  - Trial Balance Sheets - names include: Kane & Elk R.R. Co., James Mfg. Co., LaMont Chemical Co., 1921-1928 (Volume 90)
- Balance Books, Check Stub Books, and Vouchers, 1895-1923; IV.
  This series contains check stubs, vouchers, and check registers. Vouchers contain check stubs from businesses for the transportation of oil. The record of Gauger's Daily Runs consists of dates, destinations (business or individual), and monies needed or collected. These records are probably those of Eureka's debt collector.
  - Balance Book, overall balance of Co. - lists all accounts, 1895-1906 (Volume 91)
  - Notes and Bills, 1899-1905 (Volume 92)
  - Consolidated Chemical Co. check stubs, 1904-1905 (Volume 93)
  - E.E. Collins, Right of Way Department, voucher ledger, Oil City, Pa., Eureka Pipeline Co., 1906 (Volume 94)
  - Voucher book, July-August 1908 (Volume 95)
  - Check stubs, 1911-1912 (Volume 96)
  - LaMont Chemical Company, Kane Bank & Trust Company, check register, 1915-1917 (Volume 97)
  - Voucher book, 1918-1920 (Volume 98)
  - Record of Gauger's Daily Runs (debt/monies collector?), 1922-1923 (Volume 99)
- Rentals, 1906-1922; V.
  Series V contains records of the Eureka Pipe Line Company's land rentals in Allegheny and the surrounding counties. Land containing a pipe line with oil flow was essentially owned by the company, and could be rented by companies or individuals.
  - Southwest rents and taxes, 1906 (Volume 100)
  - Eureka Rentals, 1915-1918 (Volume 101)
  - Southwest Rentals, 1915-1922 (Volume 102)
- Contacts and Address Ledgers, undated; VI.
  This series includes contact and address ledgers of the Eureka Pipe Line Company. These ledgers contain alphabetized names of individuals and businesses also containing contact information.
  - Ledger. Alphabetical list of people, businesses, employees, etc. with addresses, undated (Volume 103)
  - Name index book, undated (Volume 104)
- Material in Boxes, undated; VII.
  This series consists of six record center boxes which contain letters, maps, telegraphs, audits, reports, and balance books. The material is loose within each box and appears to contain no original order or arrangement. The list of records under the box heading is a description of what was found in the box when opened for inspection (the first records seen to the last).
  - Hand written letters, maps of pipe line layout, Right of Way contracts, blueprints, indexed telegraphs, 1900-1920; Contents deals primarily with Buckeye Pipe Line Co. (Box 1)
  - Real estate audits/taxes, letters, telegraphs, 1893-1915; Contains papers from Eureka, 1893-1906 and South West Pennsylvania Pipe Line Co., 1903-1915. (Box 2)
  - Telegram books from Oil City, telegraphs of South West Pennsylvania Pipe Line Co., superintendent's summary of broken lines, 1913-1920 (Box 3)
  - Telegraphs, records, blueprints, Right of Way/damage reports, large map, profiles, letters, receipts, 1912-1924; Contains records from Eureka Pipe Line Co., South West Pennsylvania Pipe Line Co., Pure Oil PL Co., and Cumberland Pipe Line Co. (Box 4)
  - Large blueprints, telegram books with name Simmons and Oil City, 1915-1918 (Box 5)
  - Ledgers, real estate and tax statements, balance book, report of broken lines and loss of oil, over and short reports, 1907-1926; Includes materials from Eureka Co. (Box 6)
  - Unprocessed, undated (Box 7)
  - Unprocessed, undated (Box 8)
  - Records, vouchers, record for applicant for Right of Way, map, 1891-1919; Includes materials from Southern Pipe Line Company and Pipe Line. Includes maps of Susquehanna River to Millway Station (Lancaster Count, Pa.); Millway Station east to Chester County, Pa.; Chester County to Point Breeze; Pipe Line, Lower Birmingham Township and Concord Township. (Box 9)
  - Records of Buckeye Pipe Line Company, undated (Box 10)
  - Records of Cumberland Pipe Line Company, undated (Box 11)